<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Playground</title>
    <description>It&#39;s where I put the cool stuff (my experiments) that I do in topics like Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence. I am inspired by a number of bloggers around the world like Frob Yard (by Siddha Ganju http://sidgan.me), Paul Stamatiou (http://paulstamatiou.com) etc.
</description>
    <link>http://akshitarora.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://akshitarora.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 14:29:25 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 14:29:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Emotion Machine - Marvin Minsky</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is inspired from the book &quot;The Emotion Machine: Commonsense Thinking, Artificial Intelligence, and the Future of the Human Mind&quot; by Marvin Minsky, a mathematician, computer scientist, and pioneer in the field of artificial intelligence. He died at the age of 88, January 26, 2016 (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csail.mit.edu/node/2682&quot;&gt;MIT Media Lab&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/26/business/marvin-minsky-pioneer-in-artificial-intelligence-dies-at-88.html&quot;&gt;NYTimes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following are some excerpts from the book that I really found interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;h2&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;If you “understand” something in only one way, then you scarcely understand it at all -- because when you get stuck, you will have nowhere to go. But if you represent something in several ways, then when you get frustrated enough, you can switch among different points of views until you find the one that works for you.
IN AI: If a program works in only one way, then it gets stuck when that method fails. But a program that has several waysd to proceed could then swtich to some other approach, or search for a suitable substitute.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind the book is firmly opposed to the popular view that each person has a central core -- some sort of invisible spirit or self -- from which all their mental abilities originate. For what seems a demeaning idea -- that all our virtues are second hand -- or that we don&#39;t deserve credit for our accomplishments, because they come to us as gifts from some other source. Instead, I see dignity stemming from what we each have made of ourselves: &lt;b&gt;a colossal colllection of different ways to deal with different situations and predicaments.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Each of our major ways to think results from turning certain resources ON while turning others OFF and thus changing some ways that our brain behaves.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thinking&lt;/b&gt; is basically rational -- dry, detached and logical -- whereas emotions enliven our ways to think by adding irrational feelings and biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Each reader reads only what is already inside himself. A book is only a sort of optical instrument which the writer offers to let the reader discover in himself what he would not have found without the aid of the book. -- Marcel Proust 1927&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;h2&gt;CHAPTER 1: Falling in Love&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In faith, I do not love thee with mine eyes, For they in thee a thousand errors note; But &#39;tis my heart that loves what they despise. -- Shakespeare&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;When my love swears that she is made of truth, I do believe her, though I know she lies. -- Shakespeare&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;That was the beginning and the idea seemed so obvious to me that I fell deeply in love with it. And like falling in love with a woman, it is only possible if you don&#39;t know too much about her, so you cannot see her faults. The faults will become more apparent later, but after the love is strong enough to hold you to her. So I was held to this theory, in spite of all the difficulties, by my youthful enthusiasm.&quot; -- Richard Feynman (1966 Nobel Prize Lecture)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does a lover actually love? That person should be the person whom you are attached -- but if your pleasure mainly results from suppressing your questions and doubts, then you are only in love with love itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotions change the way we percieve. &lt;b&gt;Anger&lt;/b&gt; makes us more inclined to attack. &lt;b&gt;Fear&lt;/b&gt; makes us retreat from dangerous things. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;When a person you know has fallen in love, it is almost as though someone new has emerged -- a person who thinkg in other ways, with altered goals and priorities. It is almost a switch had been thrown and a different program has started to run.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-Self Concept: &lt;i&gt;Yout Self sees the world by using your senses. Then it stores what it learns in your memory. It originates all your desires and goals -- and then solves all your problems for you by exploiting your &quot;intelligence&quot;&lt;/i&gt;. Though, this concept has practical uses, it does not help us understand ourselves -- because it does not provide us with smaller parts we could use to build theories of what we are. When you think of yourself as a single thing, this gives you no clues about issues like these:&lt;br /&gt;
What determines the subjects I think about?&lt;br /&gt;
How do I choose what next to do?&lt;br /&gt;
How can I solve this difficult problem?&lt;br /&gt;
Instead, the Single-Self concept offers only useless answers like these:
My Self selects what to think about.&lt;br /&gt; My Self decides what I should do next.&lt;br /&gt; I should try to make my Self get to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Whenever you think about your &quot;Self&quot; you are switching among a huge network of models, each of which tries to irepresent some particular aspects of your mind -- to answer some questions about yourself.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 05:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://akshitarora.github.ioThe Emotion Machine - Marvin Minsky</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://akshitarora.github.ioThe Emotion Machine - Marvin Minsky</guid>
        
        
        <category>TheEmotionMachine</category>
        
        <category>Marvin</category>
        
        <category>Minsky</category>
        
        <category>ArtificialIntelligence</category>
        
        <category>Book</category>
        
        <category>AI</category>
        
        <category>MIT</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Playground!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, this is my first blog post using Jekyll. P.S. I still use &lt;a href=&quot;http://aarora.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;tumblr - Feelings :D&lt;/a&gt; for blogging. This blog is mainly intended for technical purposes. To me, the whole world is nothing but a giant experiment, so the name &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Playground&lt;/code&gt; is more like my personal playground, where I get to perform my own experiments, play around codes and publish my small accomplishments. My main research interests are Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Statistics (this is more of a pre-requisite to ML and AI :P) and Cognitive Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also a part of &lt;a href=&quot;pratik.acslab.org&quot;&gt;Applied Cognitive Science Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://iitmandi.ac.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Mandi&lt;/a&gt;. I worked under &lt;a href=&quot;faculty.iitmandi.ac.in/~varun/&quot;&gt;Dr. Varun Dutt&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Pratik_Chaturvedi&quot;&gt;Pratik Chaturvedi (Scientist ‘D’, at DTRL, DRDO, New Delhi)&lt;/a&gt;. We worked on understanding various factors that are involved in people’s interaction with natural calamities like Landslides. We first modelled the whole landslide prediction and then made a cognitive model around it to study people’s behavior. I was the one who coded the whole simulator and only recently, we actually performed the experiments and got the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was amazing! This was my first hand experience in research, doing actual experiments and it was so cool. I know every single line of code working inside that simulator (merely a tool for research). The whole 8 months process now, has been like raising a child. And those results were amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in between those 8 months, I found out that I really did enjoy research and decided to pursue it further. This blog is like my diary for every little experiment I do. Now, that I knew I had to pursue research, first work was to identify a research topic that really challenged me and something I can’t not think about every day (inspired by a TED Talk: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/scott_dinsmore_how_to_find_work_you_love&quot;&gt;How to find work you love - by Scott Dinsmore&lt;/a&gt;). Turns out, machine learning was perfect. Only recently was I asked to implement a reinforcement learning algorithm on the landslide prediction mathematical model we had built, it sparked my interest towards learning algorithms. Turns out, the concepts were not new to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, I was introduced to Machine Learning in my first year in college at an IEEE conference in my University. Back then, without much basics clear, I was unable to pursue it, but now that I have the pre-requisites, and thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://coursera.org&quot;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt; for making this one possible, I will be completing my coursework on machine learning soon. I am evolving right now, in machine learning and main objective behind setting up this blog is self-motivation. With machine learning, it has always been like “The more I discovered, the more I fell in love”. So, yeah, this is, perhaps, a new beginning in my life and this blog is all about my little playground ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There a number of people who inspired me for setting up a blog. To mention a few: &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; Siddha Ganju (sidgan) &lt;a href=&quot;http://sidgan.me&quot;&gt;http://sidgan.me&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; Paul Stamatiou &lt;a href=&quot;http://paulstamatiou.com/10-years-blogging/&quot;&gt;http://paulstamatiou.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; Derbhagya Das (Deedy) &lt;a href=&quot;http://debarghyadas.com/&quot;&gt;http://debarghyadas.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; Mark Manson &lt;a href=&quot;http://markmanson.net/&quot;&gt;http://markmanson.net/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog took me a while to set it all up, switching between different theme options, command line issues, but finally here it is. Let me make this work easy for you, if you too want to start blogging using Jekyll, these are some links you should definetly visit: &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; Jekyll documentation: &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs&quot;&gt;http://jekyllrb.com/docs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; Jekyll bootstrap: &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;http://jekyllbootstrap.com/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; The blogs by Sidgan and Deedy are good examples to look up to.&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt; Play around the code a bit, if you know some basic command line, CSS and HTML, you will understand the workaround in jekyll very easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good Bye! Cheerios!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://akshitarora.github.ioWelcome to Playground!</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://akshitarora.github.ioWelcome to Playground!</guid>
        
        
        <category>first</category>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        <category>playground</category>
        
        <category>initialize</category>
        
        <category>beginning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;Tom&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints &#39;Hi, Tom&#39; to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2016 11:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://akshitarora.github.ioWelcome to Jekyll!</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://akshitarora.github.ioWelcome to Jekyll!</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
